A Guide to the John C. Parker Papers 1874-1936
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
John C. Parker Papers 1874-1936
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2885-a
This collection consists of ca. 5 linear shelf feet of papers (21 Hollinger boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Parker collection was deposited in the Library on March 4, 1948, by Mr. John Crump Parker of Franklin, Virginia, who then made the collection a gift to the Library on January 3, 1980. An addition of ca. thiry items was given to the Library on February 5, 1951, by Mr. Parker and is held under Manuscripts Department number 2885-a.
Scope and Content Information
The Parker collection consists of ca. 5 linear shelf feet of papers (21 Hollinger boxes), 1874-1936, of John Crafford Parker, chiefly generated by his law practice and insurance business in Southampton County, Virginia. Parker was born in 1862 and attended the University of Virginia Law School from 1882 to 1884. After recieving his degree, he set up practice in Franklin, Virginia. He served as a member of the Virginia House of Delegates for Southampton County ca. 1899. He was elected a delegate from the Franklin Magisterial District to the 1904 State Democratic Convention and campaigned to have himself selected as delegate to the Democratic National Convention in St. Louis, Missouri that same year. In 1916 he was elected a delegate to the Democratic National Convention in St. Louis. In addition, Parker, a prominent Virginia Methodist, was a member of the General Conference's Board of Education of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South. He died at the age of fifty-six in December 1918.
The collection contains Parker's legal, business, and personal papers. The legal papers consist of case files and miscellaneous paper and include correspondence, legal documents or copies of documents, receipts, financial records, work sheets, notes, and sketches of property.
Mr. Parker changed his insurance firm to a partnership to be known as J.C. Paker & Sons, with his sons John Crump Parker and Alexander W. Parker being junior partners prior to 1918. Some of their papers from that period and after their father's death appear in the collection.
The legal case files chiefly concern the settlement of estates, including assistance to administrators and executors, the clarification of property rights, the formation of corporations, Parker's legal advisorship to a large company, guardianships of minors, bankruptcy, debt collection, divorce, and receivership. His insurance papers concern applications from his clients for surety bonds and fire insurance.
Most of Parker's clients lived in Franklin or Southampton County, Virginia. The major files of legal records in the collection are those pertaining to B.K. Basho, Camp Manufacturing Company, Sallie Darden, Bessie Leigh, Martha J. Newman, J.D. Pretlow, the Southern Railway, the estates of J.D., Nannie J., and P.S. Thomas, Sallie L. Hayes, and the Wynne children guardianship. The case file on Camp Manufacturing Company, Franklin, Virginia, one of the largest lumber processing companies in the early part of the twentieth century, contains the greatest number of items.
Parker's personal papers consist chiefly of his correspondence with relatives, friends, and political associates. Also included are papers concerning his work with the Board of Education of the Methodist Church and as treasurer for Southampton County. Topics mentioned in the personal correspondence include state and national politics, the Methodist Church, yellow fever in 1899, political difficulties in Mexico in 1913, investments in Cuba, and neutrality and World War I. Included in this section are several letters from Richard E. Byrd, speaker of the Virginia House of Delegates in 1912, and letters from University of Virginia faculty members John Barbee Minor, William Minor Lile, William A. Lambeth, and Raleigh C. Minor. Parker wrote in 1912 to L.J. Bain of the Virginia House of Delegates expressing his interest in establishing a university for women near Charlottesville. Also included are letters from John Stewart Bryan, William Jennings Bryan (on divisions in the Democratic Party in 1900), James Cannon, John Wood Fishburne, John Warwick Daniel, Edward Everett Holland, Eppa Hunton, William Atkinson Jones, J.E. McCulloch of the Southern Sociological Conference, Raleigh Colston Minor, Andrew Jackson Montague, Charles Triplett O'Ferrall, John Garland Pollard, Edward Watts Saunders, Henry Carter Stuart, James Hoge Tyler, and Henry St. George Tucker. Family correspondents include Parker's brothers, H.C. Parker and George H. Parker; George Parker's wife; Parker's sister, Jessie Mary Parker; sister-in-law "Nannie";and his nephew, Jesse Parker. Letters in the family correspondence chiefly concern personal and financial problems and often relate to Parker's role as the family's legal advisor.
Also included in the collection are a postal card album, a nutrition notebook, bar exam coaching notes, a draft of the Franklin Academy Company's charter application, and ledgers for insurance policies, guardianship accounts, estate settlements, and stocks.
Organization
The collection is divided into two series: I. Legal Papers, and II. Personal and Political Papers.
Series I is divided into three sub-series: A. Legal Case Files, arranged alphabetically; B. Miscellaneous Legal Papers, arranged chronologically; and C. Insurance Papers.
The sub-series of Miscellaneous Legal Papers is small and generally consists of a chronological run of documents from various cases for which there are too few documents to warrant establishment of a case file in the Legal Case Files Sub-series. However, in this sub-series there are occasional groups of papers pertianing to the same case that have been drawn together in paper insert folders and filed by the date of the earliest item.
In the Insurance Papers Sub-series the papers are divided between papers regarding surety bonds, which are arranged chronologically with case file insert folders, and paper regarding property insurance whihc are arranged alphabetically in case files. Also present in this sub-series is a bound volume containing a register of insurance policies and diagrams of buildings and the Parker sons' contract to sell the insurance business.
In Series I, related information may be found in all three sub-series.
Series II is divided into two sub-series: A. Correspondence and B. Memorabilia and Miscellaneous Papers.
Contents List
- I. Legal Papers
  - A. Legal Case Files
    - Barnes, H.T. vs. S.H. Lankford 1914-1915, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Basho, Bella K.- various cases 1908-1918, n.d., 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Beaton, E. Hunter vs. Sankey H. Faircloth 1906, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Bell, B. Thomas- debt collection 1916-1918 (Box 1)
    - Boone & Jenkins vs. H.L. Hill n.d. (Box 1)
    - Bower, J.R., et al. vs. Boykins Manufacturing Co., Inc. 1917 (Box 1)
    - Bowles, W.T. and wife w/Mrs. E.H. Holland- deeds of trust 1915 (Box 1)
    - Boyette Brothers 1917 (Box 1)
    - Britt, B.C.- notes 1909-1913, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Brock, Noah- Account Books, w/D.A. Holland, Franklin, Virginia. 1917-1922, 2 vols. (Box 1)
    - Bryant, George L.: Rosa K. Scarborough, et al. vs. George L. Bryant 1885, 1914-1915 (Box 2)
    - Bryant, Kate F., Executrix, B.R. Bryant Estate 1909-1917, n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Bunkley, Augustus, Estate 1898-1916, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Butler Brothers, Inc.- bankruptcy 1920-1922 (Box 2)
    - Butler, Robert H. 1907, 1915, 1916 (Box 2)
    - Camp Manufacturing Co. 1888-1925, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Camp Manufacturing Co. 1888-1925, n.d., 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Carson, Plennie D.- loan 1911-1913 (Box 4)
    - Carson, W.H. and Lillian- miscellaneous 1915-1917 (Box 4)
    - Claud, J.G. and others- deeds and petitions 1917 (Box 4)
    - Cobb, Addie C. vs. McClenny heirs 1915-1917 (Box 4)
    - Cobb, Corporal E.T., U.S. Army 1898-1900 (Box 4)
    - Cabb, Samuel N. and Jesse L.- deed of trust 1916 (Box 4)
    - Cobb, W.H.: Drake vs. Cobb 1914-1918, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Crumpler, E.L.: A.L. Davis vs. E.L. Crumpler 1916, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Cutchin, Osie Butler, Guardian vs. Margaret Cutchin, et al.- abandoned suits 1923-1924 (Box 4)
    - Darden, Carrie B., et al. vs. Peter Darden and A. Powell Darden, infants 1917-1918, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Darden, Sallie S., Committee for W.H. Summerell, ward, 2 folders and 1 account book 1905-1918 (Box 4)
    - Daughtry, Henry, Estate 1886, 1906-1914, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Drake, Lewis J. vs. Thaddeus D. Cutler, J.L. Barham and J.L. Barham, Jr., Trustee 1914-1918, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Drake, Lewis J.: Alex Drake vs. Lewis J. Drake, J.L Barham, and J. Langhorne Barham 1917, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Drewry, Bessie G.- See: Leigh, Bessie G. Drewry- D.B Drewry Estate (Box 5)
    - Duck, Joseph H., Estate 1908-1912, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Dundalow, John D., Estate 1936-1938 (Box 5)
    - Epps, Cleveland and Joseph vs. Harvey R. Wynne, et al. 1916-1917, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Everett, L.F., Estate 1881-1918, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Faltz, J. Willis vs. W.J. Sebrell and Robert A. Wynns 1914-1918 (Box 5)
    - Felts, John B.: Adelaide D. and Henry E. Bailey, et al. vs. John B. Felts 1916-1917, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Felts, Minnie L.- E.L. Felts Estate 1913-1917, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Ferguson, W.B. & Co. vs. R.E. Darden, et al. ca. 1891 (Box 5)
    - Floyd, Carrie M. - will of Amos F. Gardner 1916-1918 (Box 5)
    - Fosburg Lumber Co. vs. M.C. Vick 1906-1910 (Box 6)
    - Fox Children- guardianship 1894-1913 (Box 6)
    - Gardner, Amos F.- See: Floyd, Carrie M. (Box 6)
    - Gray, R.T. vs. Conwell, et al. 1900-1901, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Greenleaf Johnson Lumber, Co.: J.D. Abbitt and Greenleaf Johnson Lumber Co. - contract 1912, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Grizzard, F.P. - will 1915 (Box 6)
    - Grizzard, William R.: Katie R. Sobrell vs. William T. Grizzard 1915-1916 (Box 6)
    - Gwinn, Margaret and Ella Whitehead: Richard Jones, infant, and next friend, I.A. Luke vs. Hiers of Lewis Riddick 1916-1918 (Box 6)
    - Hall, Nannie E.: W.P. Gillette and J.T. Knight vs. Nannie E. Hall, et al. 1916-1918 (Box 6)
    - Harris, John Z. and E.M.: Grizzard Brothers and Co. vs. W.S. and D.R. Francis, et al. and C.F. and D.R. Francis, et al. vs. E.L. Marks, et al. 1915-1917, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Hayes, Sallie: The United States of America vs. Sallie L. Hayes, et al. 1897-1913 (Box 6)
    - Ivor Hardware Co.- certificate of incorporation 1915 (Box 6)
    - Johson, Violet M.- R.E.L. Watkins, guardian 1918-1932, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Johnson, Violet M.- R.E.L. Watkins, guardian 1918-1932, n.d. (Box 7)
    - Knight, Roger M., et al. vs. J.L. Barham, Administrator for J.T. Barnes, Isabella G. Barnes, et al. 1910 (Box 7)
    - Lankford, India vs. S.H. Lankford 1915 (Box 7)
    - Leigh, Bessie G. Drewry- D.B. Drewry Estate 1903-1927, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Leigh, Bessie G. Drewry- D.B. Drewry Estate 1903-1927 (Box 8)
    - Newman, Martha Johnson- John C. Parker, Guardian/Receiver 1912-1919, n.d., 4 folder (Box 8)
    - Newman, Martha Johnson- John C. Parker, Guardian/Receiver 1912-1919, n.d. (Box 9)
    - Norfleet, D.O. and P.J.- Biggs farm bonds 1907-1915, n.d. (Box 9)
    - Norfleet, Dr. J.A. 1891-1916 (Box 9)
    - Pace, W.T.- certificate of incorporation 1916, n.d. (Box 9)
    - Parker, George H. and Mary Lou- John C. Parker, Trustee 1909-1912 (Box 9)
    - Parker, Jessie M., Estate 1923-1936 (Box 9)
    - Parker, W.W., et al. vs. Brast 1897 (Box 9)
    - Person, James R.: Mary A. and Kelly R. Bishop vs. Heirs of Joseph W. Person 1914 (Box 9)
    - Pope, N. Lula 1903-1914, n.d. (Box 9)
    - Pretlow, Ann E., Estate- John D. Abbitt, Executor 1915-1916 (Box 9)
    - Pretlow, Jordan D., Estate 1885-1918, n.d., 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Pretlow, Jordan D., Estate 1885-1918, n.d., 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Pretlow, Sarah D., Estate 1905-1924, n.d. (Box 10)
    - Pretlow & Co. vs. Jason Cutchin, et al. ca. 1895 (Box 10)
    - Pretlow Peanut Co. vs. R.R. Reese 1917 (Box 10)
    - Prince, Nannie E. vs. Ida M. Woodard, et al. 1912-1915, n.d. (Box 10)
    - Randolph-Macon Case 1912 (Box 11)
    - Ridge Route- Norfolk to Richmond, Va. 1917 (Box 11)
    - Robertson, J.W. and Roxanna and E.S. Eley, Trustee- contract 1874, 1906, 1907, n.d. (Box 11)
    - Saunders, Richard and Eugene C. Smith- delinquent land taxes 1914, n.d. (Box 11)
    - Smith, Delia F.- guardian 1904-1923 (Box 11)
    - Southampton Farms- register of stock shares ca. 1920 (Box 11)
    - Southern Railway Company Cases 1910-1913, n.d., 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Sumner, Mary L., guardian for Ula B. Sumner, Lillian Sumner, and Charles E. Sumner, Jr.- account book 1895-1898 (Box 11)
    - Telephone Co. Franchise, Franklin, Va. 1905-1911, n.d. (Box 12)
    - Thomas, J. Beekman and Eunice H.- miscellaneous business 1902-1914 (Box 12)
    - Thomas, J.O., Estate 1912-1916, n.d., 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Thomas, Nannie J., Estate 1915-1922, n.d. (Box 12)
    - Thomas, P.S., Estate 1901-1917 (Box 12)
    - Thomas, P.S., Estate 1899-1917, n.d., 1 folder and 1 account book (Box 13)
    - Turner, Minnie B.- guardian 1931-1936 (Box 13)
    - Vick, Virginia, Children of: Lilliam V. Vick, infant, and Gay E. Vick, next friend, et al. vs. Ray O. Vick, Genie P. Vick and Virginia Vick 1891, 1917 (Box 13)
    - Williams, Elija N.: L.E. and Nannie Worrell vs. E.N. Williams and J.W. Griffin 1899-1900 (Box 13)
    - Williams, Sallie L. and Thomas A.- miscellaneous cases 1898-1916 (Box 13)
    - Wilson, Edna Grizzard- E.H. Grizzard, Jr., Estate 1917-1924, n.d. (Box 13)
    - Woodard, James C. and Mary A.- John C. Parker, guardian 1908-1918 (Box 13)
    - Worrell, James H., et al. vs. J.L. Barham, Administrator, et al. 1915-1918 (Box 13)
    - Worrell, Peter S. vs. Thomas Bardin and Alex Drake 1917-1918 (Box 13)
    - Wynne children- guardianship 1909-1929, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - B. Miscellaneous Legal Papers
    - Legal Papers 1874-1905 (Box 14)
    - Legal Papers 1896-1905, 5 folders (Box 15)
    - Legal Papers 1908-1917, n.d., 8 folders (Box 16)
    - Legal Papers 1916-1918, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - Legal Papers 1919-1941, n.d., 2 folders (Box 18)
  - C. Insurance Papers
    - Ledger 1884-1897 (Box 18)
      customer accounts for general merchandise, indexed; register of insurance policies and diagrams of building in Franklin, Virginia
    - Surety Bonds and Correspondence 1916-1919 (Box 18)
    - Property 1916-1918 (Box 18)
    - Contract to sell J.C. Parker & Sons insurance agency 1922 (Box 18)
- II. Personal and Political Papers
  - A. Correspondence
    - Correspondence 1888-1897 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence 1898-1913, 5 folders (Box 19)
    - Correspondence 1914-1932, n.d., 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Copy, Letter signed by members of the New York State Delegation, National Democratic Convention, Chicago, Il. 1892
  - B. Miscellaneous Personal and Political Papers
    - Parker, John C. - Treasurer, Southampton County 1897-1899, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Account, J.C. Parker, Treaurer, Southampton County, VA. 1897-1899
    - Account, J.C. Parker, Treasurer, Southampton County, Va. 1898-1899
    - Certificates 1895-1943 (Box 20)
    - Certificate of Membership of J.C. Parker and E.F. Story in the Dealers and Consumers Supply Association 1902 Jan 29
    - Post Card Album ca. 1906 (Box 21)
    - Map- Ridge Route from Norfold to Richmond and Courtland to Emporia 1917
    - J.G. Claud Land Tract ca. 1917
    - Commission from the Governor of Virginia, appointing John C. Parker a delegate at the International Convention of the World League against Alcoholism 1922
    - Map of Richmons and environs prepared for Richmond (Virginia) Battlefields and Park Corporation 1928
    - Photostat of verso of above map, bearing a description of the Corporation's program and the battles shown 1928
    - Certificate appointing John Crump Parker a Board member, Southampton County Local Board No. 1, Virginia, Selective Service System 1942
    - Notice of Auction 1946 (Box 21)
    - Notebook on "Domestic Science" and Nutrition n.d. (Box 21)
    - Bar Exam Coach Class Notes and Student Reference Notes- J. Crump Parker n.d. (Box 21)
    - Franklin Academy Company Charter Application n.d. (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous 1891-1942, n.d. (Box 21)